<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for the assuring, confirming and setling of lands and estates in Ireland at the Parliament begun at Westminster, the 17th day of September, An. Dom. 1656.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Laws, statues, etc.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1091A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175030</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61296988</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61296988</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180547</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09027)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180547)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2833:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for the assuring, confirming and setling of lands and estates in Ireland at the Parliament begun at Westminster, the 17th day of September, An. Dom. 1656.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Laws, statues, etc.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed by Christopher Higgins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title vignette: commonwealth arms.</note>
                  <note>Text in black letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Birmingham. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Land tenture --  History --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180547:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACT FOR THE Aſſuring, Confirming and Setling OF Lands and Eſtates IN IRELAND.</p>
            <p>At the Parliament begun at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>September, An. Dom.</hi> 1656.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>coat of arms of the Protectorate</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-printed by <hi>Chriſtopher Higgins,</hi> in Harts Cloſe, over againſt the Trone Church, 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:180547:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180547:2"/>
            <head>AN ACT FOR THE Aſſuring, Confirming and Setling of Lands and Eſtates IN IRELAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas by a Commiſſion under the Great-Seal of <hi>England,</hi> and Inſtructions thereunto annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Entituled, <hi>A Commiſſion and Inſtructions to Charles Fleetwood, Eſq; Lieutenant General of the Army in Ireland, Edmond Ludlow, Eſq; Lieutenant General of the Horſe, Miles Corbet, Eſq; and John Jones, Eſq;</hi> Impowering them to cauſe all the Lands therein mentioned to be forfeited to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, to be forthwith ſurveyed, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the ſatisfying of Adventurers for <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and Arrears of Officers and Souldiers, and for the Setling and Planting of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with ſecurity to the Inhabitants and ſuch as ſhall Plant the ſame, the ſaid Commiſſioners therein named, are thereby authorized to cauſe the ſaid forfeited Lands to be ſurveyed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: And whereas by further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, Entituled, <hi>Further Inſtructions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Charles Fleetwood, Eſquire, Lieutenant General of the Army in IRELAND, Edmond Ludlow, Eſquire, Lieutenant General of the Horſe, Miles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180547:3"/> Corbet, Eſquire, and John Jones, Eſquire,</hi> the ſaid Commiſſioners are thereby further authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and required, for the better ſecurity of all thoſe parts of <hi>Ireland</hi> which were to be planted with Engliſh Proteſtants; And to the end that all perſons in <hi>Ireland</hi> who had right to Articles, or to any Favor or Mercy held forth by any the Qualifications in an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Entituled, <hi>An Act for the ſetling of Ireland,</hi> might enjoy the benefit intended unto them reſpectively, to publiſh and declare, That all and every the ſaid perſons which had ſuch right to Articles, or to any Favor or Mercy held forth by any the ſaid Qualifications, ſhould before the firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> 1654. remove and tranſplant themſelves into the Province of <hi>Connaught</hi> and County of <hi>Clare,</hi> or one of them, there to inhabit and abide, and to have ſet forth to them and every of them reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch Proportions of Land, and for ſuch Eſtates and Terms, and under ſuch Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Reſervations and Covenants, as ſhould be anſwerable in value unto ſo much of his and their Eſtates, as by ſuch Articles or Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he or they were to enjoy in ſuch place and manner, as the ſaid Commiſſioners, or ſuch as they ſhould Authorize, ſhould appoint and direct; And to that end the ſaid Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were likewiſe authorized and impowered to nominate Commiſſioners under them, and to authorize them to allot to any ſuch perſon or perſons, who by Articles granted unto them, or by vertue of any the ſaid Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, were to enjoy any part of their Eſtates, a like proportion of Land by meaſure, or in value in the ſaid Province of <hi>Connaught,</hi> or County of <hi>Clare,</hi> of like Eſtate of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180547:3"/> Free-hold, Term of Years, or number of Lives, to be by them held and enjoyed in lieu or ſatisfaction of ſuch part of their Eſtate, which by ſuch Articles or Qualifications he or they were to enjoy. And whereas by a late Act, Entituled, <hi>An Act for the ſpeedy and effectual Satisfaction of the Adventurers for Lands in Ireland, and of the Arrears due to the Soldiery there, and of other Publick Debts, and for the Encouragement of Proteſtants to plant and inhabit Ireland,</hi> It is Declared, That by the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God upon the Forces of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the Rebels of <hi>Ireland</hi> are ſubdued, and the Rebellion there appeaſed and ended; And that therefore, to the end all juſt Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction might be made unto the Adventurers, Officers and Souldiers, and other perſons in the ſaid laſt recited Act mentioned, and that the Country of <hi>Ireland</hi> might be planted and ſetled with ſecurity unto ſuch as ſhould plant and inhabit the ſame, the ſaid Commiſſion and Inſtructions, and Further Inſtructions are ratified and confirmed; And whereas by the ſaid Act of Satisfaction, it is declared to whom, how, and in what manner, and at what Rates the forfeited Lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhall be divided, allotted, given, granted, ſet out and diſtributed to the ſaid Adventurers and Souldiers, and others in the ſaid Act of Satisfaction expreſſed, and that for ſo much of the ſaid Lands as ſhould be aſſigned or ſet out to the ſaid Officers and Souldiers in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of their Arrears for their Service there, and in <hi>England,</hi> by vertue of the ſaid Act of Satisfaction, the Ordering, Allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Granting, Diſpoſing and ſetling thereof
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180547:4"/> unto, and upon ſuch the ſaid Officers and Souldiers ſhould be mannaged by the then Commiſſioners of Parliament in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in ſuch ſort and manner as in and by the ſaid Act of Satisfaction is declared; And whereas by an Ordinance of his Highneſs the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and his Council, dated the Twenty third of <hi>June,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty four, Entituled, <hi>An Ordinance for the further En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of the Adventurers for Lands in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and of the Souldiers and other Planters there,</hi> It is thereby (amongſt other things) Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That for, and in conſideration of every Rent, Service, Charge or Duty, iſſuing, reſerved, charged, due or payable on, or out of the Lands, or other the Hereditaments granted or intended to and for the ſaid Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and Adventurers, or either of them, to any perſon or perſons who have duely claimed the ſame, and according to this Ordinance, ſhall have the ſame allowed and ordered, Every ſuch Adventurer and Souldier, on or out of whoſe Lands or Hereditaments the ſame ſhall be iſſuing, reſerved, charged, due or payable, ſhall have ſet forth and enjoyed to him and his Heirs for ever, ſo much Land in the County of <hi>Kildare</hi> (according to the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues of Adventurers, at ſuch meaſure as was allowed to ſuch perſon for his Adventure, in ſatisfaction whereof ſuch Lands ſo charged were allotted unto them) as would have been produced, or due for an Adventure of ſuch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſum of Money as the Purchaſe or buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of ſuch Rent, Service, Charge, or Duty ſhall be computed to amount unto, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation being thereof made and certified by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180547:4"/> ſuch perſon and perſons as ſhall be authorized by his Highneſſe the Lord Protector, with the Conſent of his Council; And whereas in purſuance of all and every the ſaid Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Inſtructions, further Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordinance for Encouragement, the ſaid Commiſſioners of Parliament, the Lord Deputy and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his Highneſſe Council for the Affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or ſome of them, have cauſed the ſaid forfeited Lands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be Surveyed, and have cauſed the Papiſt Proprietors in the Province of <hi>Leynſter, Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> (Except thoſe in the County of <hi>Clare</hi>) who had any ſuch Right to Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, or who fell within any the Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions aforeſaid, to remove and tranſplant themſelves and Families into the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Connaught,</hi> or County of <hi>Clare,</hi> and have likewiſe cauſed the Lands of all and every ſuch perſon and perſon ſo tranſplanted, to be ſurveyed, and have likewiſe by their Commiſſioners thereunto by them deputed and appointed, cauſed to be allotted and given out unto ſuch perſon and perſons, ſo removed and tranſplanted, ſuch proportions of Land in the ſaid Province of <hi>Connaught,</hi> and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Clare,</hi> or one of them, as are equall in meaſure or value to ſuch Lands, and for ſuch Eſtate and Eſtates, as the ſaid perſon and perſons ſo removed and tranſplanted, ought to have had and enjoyed in any other part of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by vertue of his, or their Articles or Qualifications.</p>
            <p>And whereas the ſaid Commiſſioners of Parliament, the Lord Deputy and Council
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180547:5"/> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his Highneſſe ſaid Council for the Affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or ſome of them, in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purſuance of the ſaid ſeveral aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Powers and Authorities, have procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by themſelves and their Commiſſioners, and others by them authorized, to allot, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, grant, aſſign, ſet out and deliver ſeveral parts, ſhares and proportions of the ſaid for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited, eſcheated and exchanged Lands of the ſaid Rebels, Papiſt Proprietors, and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted perſons, unto ſeveral Officers and Souldiers, in full or part of their reſpective Debentures, for the Arrears for their reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Services there and in <hi>England,</hi> and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other perſon and perſons, compriſed in the ſaid Commiſſion and Inſtructions, Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inſtructions, Acts and Ordinances, or ſome of them, and have likewiſe ordered, made, granted, ſet out, diſtributed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over, to ſeveral Officers and Souldiers and others, whoſe Lands ſo to them allotted, diſtributed, granted, aſſigned, ſet out and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered as aforeſaid, proved to be legally incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with any ſuch Rent, Service, Charge or Duty, as in the ſaid Ordinance of Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is expreſſed, other Lands (equal to the ſaid Incumbrance) by way of repriſal, out of the forfeited, eſcheated, or exchanged Lands in the ſaid County of <hi>Kildare,</hi> according to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the ſaid Ordinance of Encouragement as aforeſaid; All and every which ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and perſons, to whom ſuch Allotments, Diſtributions, Grants, Aſſignments and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſals were, and have been made as aforeſaid, their Leſſees or Aſſigns have entred into their ſaid ſeveral ſhares and proportions of Land,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180547:5"/> and have many of them disburſed ſeverall great ſums of Money in Buildings, Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Improvements upon the ſaid Lands ſo to them allotted, granted, aſſigned, diſtributed, ſet out, and delivered, or given in repriſal, as aforeſaid, ſo that the ſecuring and confirmation of the ſaid Allotments, Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, Grants, Aſſignments, and Repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals is now become of great uſe and neceſſity to the Plantation and Peace of <hi>Ireland;</hi> Be it therefore Enacted and Declared by his Highneſſe the Lord Protector of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and this preſent Parliament, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority thereof, That all and every Act and Acts, Thing and Things which have been done by the late Commiſſioners of the Parliament, Commiſſioners of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, Lord Deputy and Council, or the Lords of his Highneſſe Council there, or any of them, or by any other perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thereunto authorized by them, or any of them, upon, or in purſuance of the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Inſtructions, Further Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordinance for Encouragement, or any of them, for the ſurveying, allotting, ſetting forth, diſpoſing and diſtributing of any of the ſaid Rebels and Papiſts forfeited, eſcheated, or exchanged Lands, according to the true intent and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſaid Commiſſion and Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Further Inſtructions, Act of Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and Ordinance for Encouragement, or any of them; And all and every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Commiſſions, or other Authority granted by the ſaid Commiſſioners of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180547:6"/> Commiſſioners of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, Lord Deputy and Council, or by his Highneſſe ſaid Council for the Affairs of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to any perſon or perſons for the Adjudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Claims, or for the Adjudication of the Qualifications of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> or for ſetting forth of Lands unto them, And all and every Iudgment and Iudgments, Decree and Decrees, Diſpoſition and Diſpoſitions of Lands made by them, or any of them, in purſuance of their reſpective Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, And alſo all and every Diviſion, Allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Grant, Aſſignment, Order, Act and Thing already done, made, executed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, or cauſed to be done, made, executed or performed by the ſaid Commiſſioners of Parliament, Commiſſioners of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, Lord Deputy and Council of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or his Highneſſe Council for the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or any of them, or by any other perſon or perſons by Commiſſion or Authority from them, or any of them, upon, or in purſuance of the ſaid Commiſſion and Inſtructions, further Inſtructions, Act and Ordinance aforementioned, or any of them, for the diſpoſing of the ſaid Rebels and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts forfeited, eſcheated or exchanged Lands, ſhall be, and are hereby adjudged, deemed and declared to be good, firm and effectual to all intents and purpoſes, and are hereby for ever ratified and confirmed. And be it further Enacted and Declared, and it is likewiſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enacted and Declared by the Authority aforeſaid, That all and every ſuch perſon and perſons, their Heirs, Executors, Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Aſſigns reſpectively, to whom any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180547:6"/> ſuch forfeited, eſcheated or exchanged Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Caſtles, Houſes, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments have been ſo allotted, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, given, granted, diſtributed, ſet out, delivered or reprized by the ſaid Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Parliament, or Commiſſioners of the Commonwealth, the ſaid Lord Deputy and Council, or his Highneſſe ſaid Council for the Affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or any of them, or by any other perſon or perſons by Commiſſion or Authority from them, or any of them, are and ſhall be, and are hereby reſpectively adjudged and declared to be in real and actual Seiſin and Poſſeſſion of all and every ſuch Manors, Caſtles, Houſes, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, ſo to him and them allotted, aſſigned, given, granted, diſtributed, ſet out, delivered or reprized reſpectively, as aforeſaid; And that all and every ſuch perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, their Heirs and Aſſigns, ſhall, and may for ever hereafter have, hold, and enjoy the ſame to him and them reſpectively, and to his and their reſpective Heirs and Aſſigns in free and common Soccage, as of the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> under ſuch Rents, Services, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, Conditions, Qualifications, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittals, and Abatements, as in and by the ſaid ſeveral Commiſſion and Inſtructions, Further Inſtructions, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordinance for Encouragement, or any of them are expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Provided, That neither this Act, nor any thing therein, nor in the ſaid aforementioned Commiſſion and Inſtructions, Further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Encouragement, or any of them
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180547:7"/> contained ſhall any wayes extend to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, extinguiſhment, defeating, making void or prejudicing of any Contract, Bargain, Sale, Grant, Demiſe, Leaſe, Releaſe, Rent, or Exchange, heretofore made or granted of, or out of any the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated or exchanged Lands, by any the ſaid Officers or Souldiers, or others to whom the ſame have been ſo formerly allotted, aſſigned, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, granted, diſtributed, ſet out, delivered or reprized as aforeſaid, or of any Contract, Bargain, or Sale of any Debenture or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentures, in ſatisfaction whereof any the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated or exchanged Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements or Hereditaments, are, have been, or ſhall be allotted, granted, given out, or diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to any perſon or perſons whatſoever, but that all and every ſuch perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to whom any ſuch Contract, Bargain, Sale, Grant, Demiſe, Leaſe, Releaſe, Rent or Exchange, hath or have been ſo made or granted, and the Heirs, Executors, Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators, and Aſſigns of all and every ſuch perſon and perſons reſpectively, ſhall and may at all times hereafter peaceably and quietly enjoy to his and their reſpective Vſe and Vſes, the benefit and advantage of every ſuch Bargain and Contract, ſo to him and them reſpectively made as aforeſaid, Any thing in this Act, or in the ſaid Commiſſion and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, Further Inſtructions, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordinance for Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any of them, contained to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And to the end the ſaid Commiſſion and Inſtructions, Further Inſtructions, Act of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180547:7"/> Settlement, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Encouragement, may be further put in execution as to the ſaid Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, whoſe Arrears or any part thereof are yet to be ſatisfied in <hi>Ireland;</hi> Be it further Enacted and Declared, and it is further En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted and declared by the Authority aforeſaid, That the Lord Deputy and Council, or other chief Governor or Governors of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the Council there for the time being, or the Council there in the abſence of the chief Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, ſhall be, and are hereby required and authorized at all and every time and times hereafter, to do and execute, or cauſe to be done and executed, all ſuch further Act and Acts, thing and things neceſſary to be done in purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of, and according to the tenor of the ſaid Commiſſion and Inſtructions, Further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Encouragement, or any of them, as the ſaid Commiſſioners of Parliament could, might, or ought to have done thereupon, for the ſetting forth, allotting, diſtributing or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning of the remainder of the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated, or exchanged Lands, to ſuch of the Officers, Souldiers, and others, in the ſaid Act of Satisfaction mentioned, who have not yet received ſatisfaction of their reſpective Arrears; All and every which ſaid Act and Acts, thing and things hereafter ſo to be done, or cauſed to be done by the ſaid Lord Deputy and Council, or the chief Governor or Governors of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the Council there for the time being, or by the Council there in the abſence of the chief Governor, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to, and in purſuance of the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180547:8"/> and Inſtructions, Further Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordinance of Encouragement, or any of them, to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes aforeſaid, ſhall be, and are hereby decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be good, binding and effectual in Law to all intents and purpoſes. Provided, and it is hereby declared, That no ſuch further Act or Acts, thing or things ſo to be done, or cauſed to be done by the ſaid Lord Deputy and Council, or by the chief Governor or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the Council there for the time being, or by the Council there in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the chief Governor, or by any of them, or by any other perſon or perſons whatſoever by Order, Commiſſion, Authority or Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them, or any of them, ſhall any wayes alter, change, impeach, deſtroy, defeat, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh or make void all or any the ſaid for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Allotments, Aſſignments, Grants Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributions and Repriſals, or any of them, made to any the ſaid Officers and Souldiers, or other perſons afore-mentioned, by the ſaid Commiſſioners of Parliament, Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Commonwealth, Lord Deputy and Council of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his Highneſſe ſaid Council there, or any of them, or by any other perſon or perſons by Commiſſion or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from them, or any of them as aforeſaid; ſaving nevertheleſs to the ſaid Lord Deputy and Council of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the chief Governor or Governors of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the Councill there for the time being, all ſuch Power and Authority of Reſurveying any the ſaid forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, eſcheated or exchanged Lands ſo already allotted, ſet out and diſpoſed of to the Officers and Souldiers as aforeſaid, as in and by the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180547:8"/> ſaid Act of Satisfaction is expreſſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; And ſaving likewiſe to his Highneſs and the Commonwealth, all ſuch benefits and advantages of the ſurpluſage of Land which ſhall be found on the returns of the ſaid Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys, according to the tenor of the ſaid Act of Satisfaction in that behalf.</p>
            <p>And for the better and more perfect Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all and every the former Branches of this Act, Be it Enacted and Declared, and it is likewiſe Enacted and Declared by the Authority aforeſaid, That the ſaid Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty and Council, or the chief Governor or Governors of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the Council there for the time being, or the Council there in the abſence of ſuch chief Governor or Governors, ſhall be, and are hereby further authorized and required at all times hereafter (upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to them to be made) to cauſe Letters Patents, under the Great-Seal of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be made unto ſuch of the Grand Allottees, or other perſons to whom the ſaid Allotments, Aſſignments, Grants, Diſtributions or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſals of the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed Lands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> have been, or ſhall be reſpectively made as aforeſaid, or to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Heir or Heirs of ſuch Grand Allottees, or other perſons aforeſaid, in caſe of his or their Deceaſe, or to ſo many of them as ſhall deſire the ſame, for the better, more perfect, and effectual Conveyance and Aſſurance of all and every ſuch Manors, Caſtles, Houſes, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, to every ſuch perſon and perſons, his and their Heirs and Aſſigns, to be held by ſuch Tenures, and under ſuch Rents, Services, Conditions,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180547:9"/> Qualifications, Indulgences, Remittals and Abatements, as in and by the ſaid ſeverall Commiſſion and Inſtructions, Further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Encouragement, are expreſſed and declared; and in and by the ſaid Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents to create ſuch Manors, conſtituted and made up of ſuch proportion and number of Acres in the ſeveral Provinces of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and with ſuch Iuriſdictions, Liberties, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and Immunities, as in and by the ſaid Commiſſion and Inſtructions, Further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, Act of Satisfaction, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Encouragement, or any of them, is declared: And, that the ſaid Grand Allottee or Allottees, or other the ſaid Patentee or Patentees, in caſe of his or their deceaſe, ſhall for ſo much of the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated, or exchanged Manors, Caſtles, Houſes, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments to him and them ſo allotted, granted, aſſigned, ſet out, diſtributed and delivered, as ſhall juſtly belong to any other perſon or perſons, whoſe ſhares and proportions were comprehended within the General Lot of every ſuch Grand Allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, ſhall after the perfection of the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents, upon Thirty dayes warning to him or them in that behalf reſpectively given by the ſaid perſon or perſons ſo concerned, or any other perſon for their uſe as aforeſaid, and at the Coſts and Charges of him or them ſo concerned, make, execute and perfect any ſuch Aſſurance or Conveyance in the Law by Deed, Fine, Feoffment, Releaſe, Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or otherwiſe, for the ſure granting, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and conveying of all and every the ſaid
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180547:9"/> ſhare and proportion of ſuch ſeveral perſon and perſons ſo concerned, in all and every the ſaid reſpective Grand Lots, to all and every the ſaid perſon and perſons ſo concerned, and to their Heirs and Aſſigns for ever, with War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty againſt every ſuch Patentee and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees, and his and their Heirs, and all and every perſon and perſons lawfully claiming by, from, or under him and them reſpectively, as by the ſaid ſeveral perſon and perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, his or their Heirs and Aſſigns, or by his or their Counſel learned in the Law, ſhall be reaſonably deviſed, adviſed or required; And that all and every the ſaid perſon or perſons to whom ſuch Aſſurance or Aſſurances ſhall be ſo made as aforeſaid, and his and their Heirs and Aſſigns ſhall and may, and are hereby declared, immediately from and after ſuch the ſaid Aſſurance ſo to him or them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by the ſaid Patentee or Patentees, or his or their Heirs as aforeſaid, to ſtand and be ſeized of all and every ſuch ſhare and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed Lands ſo to him and them granted and conveyed as aforeſaid, to the ſeveral uſe and uſes of every ſuch Grantee, and of his and their Heirs, freed and diſcharged of and from all former Gifts, Grants, Bargains, Sales, Leaſes, Ioyntures, Dowers, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Debts, Statutes, Iudgments, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Executions and Incumbrances what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, for, or by reaſon of being ſo veſted as aforeſaid, in the ſaid Patentee or Patentees, or any of them, and ſhall accordingly hold and enjoy the ſame for ever freed and diſcharged of and from all and every the ſaid incumbrances.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:180547:10"/>
            <p>Provided nevertheleſs, and it is hereby like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe further Declared, That all and every perſon and perſons of the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Bodies Politick or Corporate, and their reſpective Heirs and Succeſſors, Executors, Adminiſtrators and Aſſigns, who have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready obtained any Decree or Decrees in the late Court of Adjudication of Claims in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or in the Court of Exchequer there, for any part of the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed Manors, Caſtles, Houſes, Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, or for any Rent out of the ſame, or for any Charge or Incumbrance thereupon, lying and being within any the Ten Counties, appointed in and by the ſaid Act of Satisfaction, for the ſatisfaction of the Adventurers, Souldiers, and others, or in the County of <hi>Lowth,</hi> or in any other County or Counties in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or who have before the Three and twentieth of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty four, exhibited his or their Claim or Claims, in the ſaid late Court for Adjudication of Claims in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſhall at or before the Firſt day of <hi>December,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty ſeven, obtain any Decree or Decrees for any the ſaid forfeited Manors, Caſtles, Houſes, Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, or for any Debt, Rent, Charge, Duty, Profit or Incumbrance ariſing, growing due out of, or charged upon the ſame, by reaſon of any Deed, Grant, Mortgage, Statute-Staple, Recognizance, Iudgment, or other Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance whatſoever in the ſaid Court of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, or who ſhall on or before the firſt day of <hi>June,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180547:10"/> God, One thouſand ſix hundred fifty eight, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any Decree or Decrees for any part of the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated, or exchanged Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments lying and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any other County or Counties in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> beſides the ſaid Ten Counties, and the ſaid County of <hi>Lowth,</hi> or for any Debt, Rent, Charge, Duty or Incumbrance, ariſing or growing due out of the ſame, or thereon char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged or chargeable as aforeſaid, ſhall and may for ever hereafter have, hold, poſſeſs and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy all and every ſuch of the ſaid forfeited, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheated or exchanged Manors, Caſtles, Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, or the ſaid Debt, Rent, Charge, Annuity, Duty or Profit ariſing or growing due out of the ſame, ſo to him or them decreed or to be decreed as aforeſaid, for and during the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Eſtate and Eſtates ſo to him and them decreed, according to the tenor and effect of every ſuch Decree ſo by him or them obtained, or to be obtained as aforeſaid, Any thing afore in this Act contained to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided nevertheleſs, and it is Enacted and Declared by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any the ſaid Perſon or Perſons, Bodies Politick and Corporate, who have any ſuch Incumbrance upon any the ſaid forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, eſcheated or exchanged Manors, Caſtles, Houſes, Lands, Tenements, or Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhall not exhibit and proſecute his or their Claim to the ſame with effect, to the obtaining his or their Decree or Decrees for the ſame, within the reſpective times to that end appointed as aforeſaid, That then
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180547:11"/> and from thenceforth all and every ſuch the ſaid perſon and perſons, Bodies Politick and Corporate, who had any ſuch right to any ſuch Incumbrance as aforeſaid, and the Heirs and Succeſſors, Executors and Adminiſtrators of every ſuch perſon and perſons, Bodies Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick and Corporate, and every of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, ſhall for ever be from thenceforth reſpectively barred to make his or their Claim to the ſame; And that then and from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated and exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Manors, Caſtles, Houſes, Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Hereditaments, ſhall be, and are hereby adjudged and declared to be for ever freed and diſcharged of and from all and every the ſaid Incumbrances reſpectively, Any thing afore in this Bill contained to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Saving likewiſe, and reſerving out of this Bill unto the Provoſt, Fellows and Scholars of the Colledge of the Holy and Vn-divided Trinity at <hi>Dublin,</hi> all ſuch Right of Action and Entry, Condition, Poſſeſſion, Reverſion, Remainder, Annuity, Rent and Common, which they have, or ought to have in or out of the ſaid forfeited, eſcheated, or exchanged Lands in this Act mentioned, or any of them.</p>
            <p>And alſo, ſaving and reſerving to all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon and perſons, who were Proteſtants on the ſaid three and twentieth day of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fourty one, and have ſo continued ever ſince, all ſuch Right, Title, Intereſt, Benefit and Advantage, which they, or their Heirs, or the Executors or Adminiſtrators of them, or any of them, have or may have, in, to, or out of any the ſaid for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180547:11"/> eſcheated or exchanged Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Hereditaments, by vertue of any Articles, or by vertue of any Compoſition, Indempnity or Exemption upon, or in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of any Articles, or of one Ordinance of his Highneſs the Lord Protector and his Council, dated the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred fifty four, Entituled, <hi>An Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance for Indempnity to the Engliſh Proteſtants of the Province of Munſter in Ireland;</hi> or by vertue of one other Ordinance of his ſaid Highneſſe and Council, dated the ſecond day of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred fifty four, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>An Ordinance for admitting Proteſtants in Ireland to Compound;</hi> which ſaid Articles, and laſt mentioned Ordinances, and all Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions made or to be made thereupon, or in purſuance thereof, are hereby likewiſe Ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Confirmed, or by any or either of them.</p>
            <p>And alſo, ſaving to all other perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have been pardoned by his ſaid Highneſſe, or admitted to compound for his or their Eſtates in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the benefit of his and their reſpective Pardons and Compoſitions, Any Law, Ordinance or Act of Parliament to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, That this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not be prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to any perſon or perſons, their Heirs or Aſſigns, for any Lands, Tenements or Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments, given or granted to him or them, or any in truſt for him or them, or his or their Heirs, ſince the firſt day of <hi>November,</hi> one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred fourty one, by or in purſuance of any Act or Acts, Ordinance or Ordinances, Order or Orders of Parliament, or of his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:180547:12"/> Highneſſe and Council, or either of them; but that every ſuch perſon and perſons, and his and their reſpective Heirs, or ſuch as they are intruſted for, and their Heirs, ſhall and may have and enjoy all and every the ſaid Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, according to the purport, true intent and meaning of all and every the ſaid Acts, Ordinances and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders reſpectively, Any thing in this Act, or any other Act of Parliament to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, That this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not ſettle upon any Officer, Souldier, or any other perſon, more then his or their firſt Proportions and due Allotments.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, and be it hereby Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That nothing in this preſent Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſhall be conſtrued or taken to Ratifie, Confirm, or Eſtabliſh the Eſtate or Poſſeſſion of <hi>Edward Dendy</hi> Serjeant at Arms, in any Manors, Lands, Tenements or Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Barony of <hi>Slayn</hi> in the County of <hi>Eaſt-Meath</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> againſt Sir <hi>John Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi> Knight and Baronet, Sir <hi>Gilbert Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> Sir <hi>William Maſham,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Everard,</hi> Baronets; Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Wharton,</hi> Sir <hi>Jacob Garet,</hi> Knights; <hi>Alexander Pym, Edward Turner,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſqs</abbr> 
               <hi>William</hi> and <hi>John Arnold,</hi> or any others who were Adventurers for the reducing of the ſaid Nation, by vertue of the Act made in the ſeventeenth year of the late King <hi>Charls,</hi> and whoſe Lots are fallen in the ſaid Barony of <hi>Slayn,</hi> or againſt any of their Heirs or Aſſigns; but that they be left to their ſeveral Remedies and Proceedings for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:180547:12"/> the making good of their Rights and Titles according to the Law.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, That neither this Act, nor any thing therein contained, ſhall extend to the prejudice of any Adventurer or Adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers for Lands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> their or any of their Heirs or Aſſigns, nor to any Honors, Caſtles, Manors, Lands, Tenements or Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that are granted, aſſigned, or duely ſet apart, allotted, or fallen by Lot, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Surveys and Returns by which the ſame was made for toward the ſatisfaction of the ſaid Adventurers, their Heirs or Aſſigns, or any of them, within the Moiety of the ſaid Ten Counties aſſigned to the Adventurers, and within the County of <hi>Lowth</hi> (except the Barony of <hi>Atherdy</hi>) and except all ſuch Lands and Hereditaments as are already duely Compounded for by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, within the ſaid Ten Counties and County of <hi>Lowth,</hi> by vertue of the aforeſaid Ordinances of his Highneſſe and Council, of the firſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and ſecond of <hi>September,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty and four.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-printed by <hi>Chriſtopher Higgins,</hi> in <hi>Harts</hi> Cloſe, over againſt the Trone Church. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
